<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The manifold practises and attempts of the Hamiltons, and particularly the present Duke of Hamilton now generall of the Scottish Army to get the crown of Scotland. Discovered in an intercepted letter written from a malignant here in London to his friend in Scotland. The letter is directed thus on the back, For the much honoured, 21.53.7.10.19.72.67.40.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89885</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N396</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E446_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202962</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863081</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863081</idno>
            <idno type="VID">161773</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89885)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 161773)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 70:E446[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The manifold practises and attempts of the Hamiltons, and particularly the present Duke of Hamilton now generall of the Scottish Army to get the crown of Scotland. Discovered in an intercepted letter written from a malignant here in London to his friend in Scotland. The letter is directed thus on the back, For the much honoured, 21.53.7.10.19.72.67.40.</title>
                  <author>Nedham, Marchamont, 1620-1678, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>23, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the year 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A malignant = Marchamont Nedham?.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June. 6th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hamilton, William Hamilton, --  Duke of, 1616-1651.</term>
               <term>Hamilton family --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:161773:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The manifold PRACTISES And Attempts of the Hamiltons, And particularly of the preſent Duke of Hamilton Now Generall of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Army To get the Crown of SCOTLAND.</p>
            <p>Diſcovered in an intercepted LETTER WRITTEN From a Malignant here in <hi>London</hi> to his friend in SCOTLAND.</p>
            <p>The Letter is directed thus on the back, <hi>For the much Honoured,</hi> 21. 53. 7. 10. 19. 72. 67. 40.</p>
            <p>Printed at LONDON, in the year 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:161773:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:161773:2"/>
            <head>The Practiſes and Attempts of the <hi>Hamiltons,</hi> particularly of Duke <hi>Hamilton</hi> now Generall of the Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Army.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He newes of ſuppreſſing thoſe Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which were the firſt movers, and chief Authors of all our troubles theſe ten yeers paſt, the taking of <hi>Barwick</hi> and <hi>Carliſle,</hi> the forward proceedings of your Parliament, and the readineſſe of an <hi>Army</hi> to advance into <hi>England</hi> for the Kings ſervice, give great encouragement to all our friends here; But the report of Duke <hi>Hamiltons</hi> being made Generall, is like water to our wine, and afflicts us with fears. It is a wonder how the Kings friends have been induced to conſent unto it, or what neceſſity could drive them to make uſe of ſo deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate a remedy, which for my own part I fear, wil prove a means to increaſe the diſeaſe, and (if God prevent not) fatall to the King and his poſterity. For now the <hi>Hamil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> have not only the pen and the purſe of <hi>Scotland,</hi> (the Dukes brother <hi>Lanerick</hi> being Secretary, and his brother in law, Treaſurer) both which have great influence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Subject; But they have the ſword ſetled in their hands by authority, and ſo whom favour will not draw
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:161773:3"/>
power will force to go along with their deſignes, for ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the Crown and Government of that Kingdome, which they have aimed at for one hundreth and twenty years and upward, as may be clearly inſtanced in many particulars, ſufficiently known to all ſuch as are acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the State of affairs of <hi>Scotland</hi> in latter times. I ſhall briefly put you in minde of ſome, and leave the reſt to your own obſervation.</p>
            <p>After the death of King <hi>Iames</hi> the fourth, <hi>Iohn</hi> Duke of <hi>Albany</hi> being choſen to governe the King in his mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. The Hamiltons made a conſpiracy to thruſt the Duke out of authority, and to take the cuſtody of the King, and Governement of the Kingdome into their own hands, the better to accompliſh their ends: In pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance whereof they took the Caſtle of <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> and made an Aſſembly of their faction. But the Duke of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banies</hi> ſpeedy comming with an Army, ſurpriſed them, diſſolved that Aſſembly, and made the Earle of <hi>Arran,</hi> chiefe of that deſigne, to flee away. But here they reſted not.</p>
            <p>For Sir <hi>Iames Hamilton,</hi> baſtard ſonne to the Earle of <hi>Arran,</hi> conſpired the death of the King in his owne houſe at <hi>Holy-rude Houſe;</hi> For which and other crimes after mentioned, divers years after, when the Plot was revealed, he was executed.</p>
            <p>When this failed, they uſed their endeavours that the King ſhould not marry, that ſo he wanting iſſue, <hi>Hamilton</hi> might ſucceed to the Crown. They hindred the Kings meeting with his Vncle the King of <hi>England,</hi> who was willing to have married his only daughter to him, and made him King of <hi>England</hi> as well as <hi>Scotland</hi> after his death.</p>
            <p>The King going by ſea to <hi>France,</hi> Sir <hi>Iames Hamilton</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:161773:3"/>
went with him to hinder his marriage; and the King being aſleep in the ſhip, Sir <hi>Iames</hi> without any neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty from wind or weather, cauſed the mariners to turne ſaile from the Weſt Coaſt of <hi>England,</hi> and to land in <hi>Galloway;</hi> which gave the King ſuch cauſe of diſcontent, againſt Sir <hi>Iames,</hi> as he began to underſtand his unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full dealing, and at laſt he was executed for Treaſon.</p>
            <p>Theſe practices diſcovered, made the King more ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty to marry, that his ſucceſſion might put the Hamil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons out of hope, and himſelfe out of danger of their fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther plots.</p>
            <p>The King dying, and leaving iſſue, only one daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſix dayes old, The <hi>Hamiltons</hi> thought all their own; For they got the Earle of <hi>Arran</hi> to be named Governour by a private faction: But the Eſtates ſoone weary of his Government, diſcharged him of his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; wherefore his deſigne, to marry his ſonne upon the Queen (whom he keeped rather like a priſoner, then a Princeſſe) was diſappointed, though in the opinion of divers, it was once farre advanced; the Duke of <hi>Lenox</hi> and Earle of <hi>Angus,</hi> his principall oppoſer, one of them being by him baniſhed, and the other impriſoned.</p>
            <p>After the Queen and her mother were reſcued out of his hands, in hopes to gaine their favour, and ſo his ends he abjured his religion in Sterling, but without ſucceſſe. When neither he could get the Queen out of the way, nor married as he deſired, he conſented to expoſe her to the ſtormes of the ſea, and danger of enemies, and ſold her to France, for which he was made Duke of <hi>Chaſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rault.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having in manner thus ſold their pretence to the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of the Crown, yet the Hamiltons were not quiet, but uſed many meanes, during the Queens being in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:161773:4"/>
               <hi>France,</hi> and after her return to get the Crown. In or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whereunto they conſpired with the Earle of <hi>Bothu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> to kill the Earle of <hi>Murray,</hi> and when the Queen married to the houſe of <hi>Lennox,</hi> which to this day, they eſteemed alwayes as their great enemy, they conſpired with the Earle of <hi>Bothuel</hi> to murther the King, wherein particularly Biſhop <hi>Hamilton</hi> Duke <hi>Hamilton</hi> of <hi>Chastle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rault</hi> brother was very inſtrumentall. When the King was thus removed, and ſo the Crown brought a degree nearer to the houſe of <hi>Hamilton,</hi> it ſeemed to them ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry probable (as it was indeed) that <hi>Bothuel</hi> ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the young King, and not ſuffer him to live to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge his fathers death, and prejudge the children of <hi>Bothuel</hi> with the Queen in the ſucceſſion to the Crown, and if the King were deſtroyed, they hoped that the Queen and <hi>Bothuel</hi> would be ſo hatefull to the people, for the murther of her husband and her ſonne, that they would have eaſie acceſſe to the Crown, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then that they might kil <hi>Bothuel;</hi> in which caſe they were in hope the Queen ſhould marry, <hi>John Hamilton</hi> the Dukes ſonne, whom ſhe entertained, often with merry looks and chearfull countenance. But the King being preſerved and the Queen keeped in <hi>Loch-herm</hi> by command of the Parliament, the Hamiltons took ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther courſe, which was to relieve the Queen, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy all their power, to ſuppreſſe the King, and the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie that adhered to him</p>
            <p>I might here make a large diſcourſe of their baſe mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering the Regent the Earle of <hi>Murray,</hi> their joyning in conſpiracy with the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> and others in <hi>England</hi> againſt Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> their pretending to have the Queen brought out of <hi>England,</hi> when they knew it was impoſſible, without the Queen of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:161773:4"/>
favour which they never ſought but rejected, to the end they might in the meane time have the better opportunity, to follow out their deſignes againſt the King, and hinder him from being ſetled in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment (as now they pretend the reſcuing of the King out of the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> and yet by their actions I am afraid ſhall render it impoſſible,) But I leave theſe and other remarkeable paſſages, that I may come near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er our own times to ſpeak of the deſignes of this <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe,</hi> whom cunning policie and jugling carriage (ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded with the Craft and Courage of his brother <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerick</hi>) ſeemes to have fitted for ſuch an enterpriſe, and who began very early to inſiſt in the ſteps of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors, encouraged perhaps with that old Scotch Propheſie.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>When <hi>Kaidyow</hi> ſhall be King.</l>
                  <l>Meikle woeſhall be bring.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>His firſt Plot to get power into his hands was under pretext of that levie for <hi>Germanie</hi> about ſeventeene or eighteene yeeres agoe; whereof that you may have a true narration, <hi>I</hi> ſhall give you the chief heads of the depoſitions of the Lord <hi>Reay,</hi> Lord <hi>Ochilcree</hi> and others, as their examinations were taken by the Lord <hi>Coventry</hi> then keeper of this kingdome; treaſurer <hi>VVeſton,</hi> the Earles of <hi>Morton</hi> and <hi>Carliſle,</hi> by the Kings directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>In <hi>anno</hi> 1630 three or foure conſiderable perſons of the name of <hi>Hamilton</hi> of neere relation to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe of <hi>Hamilton,</hi> not having ſerved the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> one yeere, caſhiered themſelves from ſervice, without any known cauſe to ſuch as were their fellow
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:161773:5"/>
ſouldiers; the Lord <hi>Reay</hi> being in <hi>Stockholme</hi> at the ſame time, was informed by his Lievtenant Colonel, one <hi>Lindſey,</hi> who lodged in the ſame houſe with Sir <hi>James Hamilton</hi> that the reaſon was, their chiefe the Marqueſſe of <hi>Hamilton</hi> intended to be a ſouldier, and they reſolved to take a ſhare of his fortune whatſoever it ſhould be, and that they had aſſigned their eſtates to others before their engagement, that they had offered him the ſaid <hi>Lindſey</hi> a Regiment whereof he did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, and that they ſhortly expected <hi>David Ramſey</hi> from <hi>England,</hi> who accordingly not many dayes after came to <hi>Sweden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In company one night, as the Lord <hi>Reay</hi> Colonel <hi>Alexander Hamilton,</hi> Sir <hi>James Hamilton</hi> and <hi>David Ramſey,</hi> were drinking, they did drinke the Marqueſſe of <hi>Hamiltons</hi> health by the name of <hi>James by the grace of God King of Scotland,</hi> and in diſcourſe <hi>David Ramſey</hi> complained to him of the great abuſes in the Court, and that Popery and Arminianiſme exceedingly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed to which the Lord <hi>Reay</hi> replying, that there was no remedy but patience, nay ſayes <hi>David Ramſey</hi> (with a great oath) to uſe your own words my Lord, <hi>VVe muſt help God to amend it.</hi> Further ſaid, that the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe</hi> was a good Proteſtant, and before it were long, he would let the world ſee his deſigne was for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of his Religion, the Lord <hi>Reay</hi> anſwered that it would be ſmall advantage to us to procure a free paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of the Goſpel in <hi>Germany,</hi> if we loſt it at home, to which <hi>David Ramſey</hi> ſaid, there were many honeſt men at home, and that the <hi>Marqueſſe</hi> would make uſe of his Army to protect them, and that this was his onely aym. Whereupon the Lord <hi>Reay</hi> offered his ſervice in that quarrell: <hi>David Ramſey</hi> ſaid it was not needfull to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:161773:5"/>
any more to him of the buſineſſe, he muſt keepe his maſters ſecret; but if there was any thing the Lord <hi>Reay</hi> deſired to be done for him in <hi>England,</hi> he could do his Lordſhip ſervice; Colonell <hi>Hamilton</hi> and Sir <hi>James</hi> being to go for <hi>England,</hi> the Lord <hi>Reay</hi> deſired to have the reverſion of <hi>Orkney,</hi> ſaying it were for the advantage of the Marqueſſe his ends to have a friend in that place; and on the morrow Colonel <hi>Alexander Hamilton</hi> and <hi>David Ramſey</hi> having given him great aſſurance of true friendſhip from their maſter the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe, if he would continue conſtant in reſolution, they deſired him to write a generall Letter to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe with the two Colonels; which he did, and ſo they parted.</p>
            <p>In the Moneth of <hi>July,</hi> Maſter <hi>Robert Meldrum</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come from the Marqueſſe in purſuance of that ſame deſigne, the Lord <hi>Reay</hi> met with him in <hi>Pomerland,</hi> and aſked newes from <hi>England,</hi> to which Maſter <hi>Meldrum</hi> anſwered that matters became worſe and worſe, and the King did give greater way to Papiſts and Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians then before; then he aſked the Lord <hi>Reay</hi> where his Coſen <hi>David Ramſey</hi> was, and what he had done; and the Lord <hi>Reay</hi> told him that he was gone for <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and all things were done according to his mind, and particularly that he had taken care for Armes and Ammunition to be ſent to the Marqueſſe from <hi>Sweden;</hi> at which newes Maſter <hi>Meldrum</hi> did throw his cap to the ground and jumped up, calling aloud, <hi>good newes, good newes, I am a happy man, I am happy and made up for ever, I thanke God my five yeeres paines are not loſt;</hi> my good Lord <hi>Reay,</hi> is this true? To which the Lord <hi>Reay</hi> replying that it was true, and that he had a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicat of the contract, and was engaged in the buſines
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:161773:6"/>
to <hi>David Ramſey,</hi> and the two Colonels and to the Marqueſſe by Writ. Maſter <hi>Meldrum</hi> ſaid, O my Lord, that was the worke of God, and not man, to inſpire your Lordſhip to joyne with us.</p>
            <p>Further Maſter <hi>Meldrum</hi> told to <hi>Lindſay</hi> my Lord <hi>Reays</hi> Lieutenant Colonel, that ſix thouſand trayned ſouldiers with their own Faction in the Countrey would be able to do the buſineſſe.</p>
            <p>The day following at Colonel <hi>Leſlies</hi> Tent, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Meldrum</hi> told the Lord <hi>Reay</hi> that King <hi>Charles</hi> was created for nothing but for deſolation and undoing of kingdomes, Religion and people, and there was no way left, but to take him and immure him within a wall or Dungeon for ever. The Lord <hi>Reay</hi> demanded how that could be got done; Maſter <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drum</hi> anſwered, that the way was eaſie; for after the men were levyed in <hi>Scotland</hi> they might take one moneth to traine them at <hi>Leith</hi> without any ſuſpition, then they might ſeiſe on the Caſtles of <hi>Edinburgh Sterling</hi> and <hi>Dumbartan</hi> and the Town of <hi>Barwick</hi> in one night, and having fortifyed <hi>Leith,</hi> then to enter <hi>England</hi> by open force.</p>
            <p>Further, he told that the Lord <hi>Reay</hi> that he was wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a Declaration concerning the Marqueſſe his juſt and cleere title to the Crown, and touching the tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall uſage and ſufferings of the Church under King <hi>James</hi> in his laſt dayes, and now worſe, groaning un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Son.</p>
            <p>Within a few dayes there came newes of the birth of the Prince, and the Lord <hi>Reay</hi> aſked M. <hi>Meldrum</hi> whether this would coole the Marques his intentions, to which maſter <hi>Meldrum</hi> ſighing, ſaid, not, If the King and Queen of <hi>Bohemia</hi> would give their daughter to the Marqueſſe,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:161773:6"/>
as they had promiſed; making no queſtion or difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty about the Marqueſſe his divorcing from his preſent wife, which (as <hi>David Ramſey</hi> had affirmed) was a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry beaſt, and the King had forced him to marry her.</p>
            <p>Alſo Maſter <hi>Meldrum</hi> being in company drinking with Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Lindſay</hi> and on <hi>Henry Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>champ</hi> an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentleman, he did diſcover ſo much of that buſineſſe, as the morrow after the Lieutenant Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel told the Lord <hi>Reay</hi> he thought Maſter <hi>Meldrum</hi> the worſt Secretary in the world.</p>
            <p>Maſter <hi>Meldrum</hi> in diſcourſe one day with the King of <hi>Swedens</hi> Secretary ſaid, it were greatly for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> whoſe ambition was without limits, that the Marqueſſe did raiſe warre in <hi>Britaine;</hi> for if the King of <hi>sweden</hi> had a deſigne on <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke,</hi> the King of <hi>Britain</hi> ſhould not be able to help his Unckle; Whereunto the Secretary replyed, that they feared not the King of <hi>Britain;</hi> for he that would not help his owne Siſter, would never helpe his Unckle.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Reay</hi> aſked Maſter <hi>Meldrum</hi> what they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to do with the Queene and Prince, he anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that they would ſhut up the child with his father, and ſend the Queen to her Mother, to be put into a Monaſtery.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Meldrum</hi> further acquainted the Lord <hi>Reay,</hi> that the Marqueſſe would take pledges of all in <hi>Scotland</hi> who would not joyne with him, or make them priſoners, and that he the ſaid Maſter <hi>Meldrum</hi> was to be Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of State.</p>
            <p>When the Lord <hi>Reay</hi> came to <hi>Holland</hi> in <hi>March</hi> 1631 he met with <hi>David Ramſey,</hi> who delivered him a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from the Marqueſſe, of complement and thanks, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:161773:7"/>
told him that all went right with the Marqueſſe, that he had gotten from the King ten thouſand pounds in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> and the Wine cuſtomes in <hi>Scotland</hi> for divers yeeres, which he would ſell, and that all things pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded without obſtacle, only the ſtay was for Armes and Ammunition; afterwards he ſaid he had ill newes to tell the Lord <hi>Reay,</hi> which was, that the Marqueſſe his wife was brought to bed of a child; but for the buſines of <hi>Orkney,</hi> that the Lord <hi>Reay</hi> might have it cheaper then to pay the duties of it, and that when the Lord <hi>Reay</hi> met with the Marqueſſe, he would infuſe that into him which he the ſaid <hi>David Ramſey</hi> durſt not.</p>
            <p>He ſaid further, that the King had made a Peace with <hi>Spaine</hi> very prejudiciall to <hi>Holland,</hi> and that the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer <hi>Cottington</hi> and others had muffled the King to bar the <hi>Hollanders</hi> from the fiſhing, which might fall out happily for them.</p>
            <p>When the Lord <hi>Reay</hi> came to <hi>England,</hi> the Lord <hi>Hamilton</hi> did give him many thanks, aſſuring him he would not want him, that he ſhould have what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions he deſired, and that he had written to the king of <hi>Sweden</hi> with <hi>Elphingſtonn</hi> and <hi>Meldrum</hi> that he would detaine him, and if he would hazard with him the ſaid Marqueſſe in this buſineſſe, that it ſhould be a tye for ever upon him and his poſterity.</p>
            <p>In the beginning of <hi>May</hi> 1631, the Lord <hi>Reay,</hi> meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Lord <hi>Ochiltry</hi> at the Beare of the Bridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot, he ſaid to the Lord <hi>Ochiltry,</hi> your Lordſhip is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter acquainted with the Lawes of the Land then I, who am a ſouldier and have lived abroad; I do therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to know, what danger it is if a man ſhould heare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad any Plot againſt the king and ſtate, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale it; The Lord <hi>Ochiltry</hi> anſwered that it was the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:161773:7"/>
loſſe of life and eſtate; and within eight or ten days after, upon promiſe of ſecrecy not to divulge it without his adviſe and direction, the Lord <hi>Reay</hi> communicated the whole buſineſſe to the Lord <hi>Ochiltry.</hi> After revealing of it, they reſolved firſt to acquaint the Lord Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of <hi>England</hi> therewith, that he might impart it to the king, and accordingly the Lord <hi>Ochiltry</hi> did acquaint the Lord Treaſurer with it, and afterward upon the 18 of <hi>May,</hi> the Lord <hi>Reay</hi> delivered in a relation of all the particulars before mentioned, under his hand, which he offered likewiſe to ſeale with his blood.</p>
            <p>The Marqueſſe of <hi>Hamilton</hi> being then in <hi>Scotland</hi> upon ſecret advertiſement from a friend at Court, came ſpeedily to the king, who at firſt entertained him not with that familiarity he was wont; but by his cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning policy, and ſubtile inſinuations he prevailed over the kings good nature, perſwading him to beleeve that all was done out of malice, and that theſe were aſperſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and calumnies invented by the Lord <hi>Ochiltry,</hi> whom he cauſed the King to ſend to <hi>Scotland</hi> to be there tryed and cenſured, well knowing, that at ſuch a diſtance from the King he could order the matter as he pleaſed.</p>
            <p>It is to be obſerved that the Lord <hi>Ochiltry,</hi> confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with the Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> who was deſirous to be informed of the Marqueſſe of <hi>Hamiltons</hi> power and ſtrength in <hi>Scotland,</hi> with more forwardneſſe and affection, then due conſideration, did give in a liſt of the names of the friends of the Marqueſſe, whom he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended would be moſt ready to joyne with the Marqueſſe, and that when the Marqueſſe returned from <hi>Scotland</hi> to Court, he ſuggeſted to the King that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:161773:8"/>
there might be preſent danger to his perſon, by ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Marqueſſe, who was the prime Agent to come neer him. In theſe particulars it is true, that the Lord <hi>Ochiltry</hi> had no warrant from the Lord <hi>Reay,</hi> to deliver in a liſt of names to the Treaſurer, nor to ſay to the King, that he was in preſent danger by the returne of the Marqueſſe from <hi>Scotland;</hi> But all the reſt of the particulars the Lord <hi>Reay</hi> did acknowledge, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver in ſubſcribed with his hand: yet the Lord <hi>Reay</hi> was not at all challenged for any information he had given, nor the Lord <hi>Ochiltry,</hi> for any thing he had ſaid by warrant from the Lord <hi>Reay,</hi> but ſuch was the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the <hi>Marqueſſe,</hi> as the Lord <hi>Ochiltry</hi> was arraigned for delivering in that liſt of names, and ſuggeſting to the king his feares of his Majeſties danger, upon the Marqueſſe his returne; and his friends perceiving, after <hi>Ochiltry</hi> had pleaded for his own innocency, that the matter reliſhed otherwiſe then was expected, found wayes to put off further Tryal, and to impriſon him, firſt in <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> there after in the blackneſſe that he might be out of the way, and at further diſtance from the King, who was then comming to <hi>Scotland;</hi> in which priſon he lyeth ſtill, the matter never yet being put to any legall tryal, nor he declared guilty or not guilty, notwithſtanding his frequent petitions for the ſame. The Lord <hi>Reay</hi> in the meane time who was the chiefe informer, not at all to this day troubled or accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, which no queſtion if the Marqueſſe had not been conſcious to his own guiltineſſe, could not have come to paſſe; however it is well known to ſome at Court, what power <hi>David Ramſey</hi> had over the Marqueſſe all his life; and that when he was reduced to any ſtrait or want, if the Marqueſſe furniſhed him not readily, or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:161773:8"/>
ſuch ſuits from the King as he deſired, he would vow and ſweare to diſcover that the Marqueſſe was a Traitor, after which he hath been ſecretly brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Marqueſſe his lodging, his deſires granted, and they reconciled. And it is likewiſe well known, that Maſter <hi>Meldrum</hi> hath a penſion from the Marqueſſe yearly.</p>
            <p>I might here adde the examinations, touching Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Meldrum,</hi> and others about this buſineſſe; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I promiſed to be brief, I ſhall only adde the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of one Maſter <hi>l. Borthwick,</hi> which he delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the King ſigned with his hand, that you may underſtand what ſort of people theſe be; the words which he depoſeth <hi>Meldrum</hi> to have ſaid are theſe.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Domum Regis eſſe profluvium iniquitatis &amp; foeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum lupanar.</item>
               <item>2. Reginam eſſe omnium mulierum ſalaciſſimam.</item>
               <item>3. Flagellum dei inhaerere univerſae familiae &amp; ſtirpi <hi>Jacobi</hi> Regis.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The next attempt of the Marqueſſe to get power in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his hands was in the beginning of the troubles of <hi>Scotland,</hi> upon occaſion whereof he procured to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to go to that Kingdome, to ſettle all differences there; but if we may judge of his intentions by his actions and the iſſue, that was not his errand to <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> but to increaſe the differences; for when after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny juglings between King and ſubject, he put all over to the determination of the Nationall Synod at <hi>Glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gow,</hi> then within ſeven or eight dayes diſſolved it, and returned to the King, whom he incenſed againſt his Subjects of <hi>Scotland,</hi> as he had done them againſt their
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:161773:9"/>
King, hoping to fiſh in muddy waters. A war follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the Marqueſſe purchaſed to himſelfe the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Navy, that whatſoever danger the King ſhould be in, the Marqueſſe himſelfe might be in ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and look on as a ſpectator. When he came to the fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h of <hi>Scotland,</hi> he acted his part at ſea, as he had done in the land; None could diſcerne whether he was for the King or the Countrey; he did weare the Kings colours; but was very ſparing of his men and ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, neither indeed was it ſafe for him to do otherwiſe; for the Covenanters ſent ſome into the ſhips to him, to let him know that if he did any harme, they would diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover and make good all the buſineſſe, of which he was accuſed by the Lord <hi>Reay</hi> and <hi>Ochiltry;</hi> which no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion they could very well have done, Maſter <hi>Meldrum</hi> being then a forward Covenanter.</p>
            <p>When a pacification was made betwixt the King and his ſubjects of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the Scots entred this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome the year following, the Marqueſſe ſtill kept cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with the chiefe Covenanters: and if ſome of the Scots Commiſſioners had not for Court ends ſtood his friends, in the beginning of this Parliament, he had ſuffered, for his abuſing both King and people; for ſome Articles were once in preparation by the Houſe of Commons for his counſelling the King to the breach of pacification, for betraying the Kingdome to the Scots, for the multitude of his Monopolies, his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing the King to wracke Maſter <hi>Trew</hi> a member of the Houſe of Commons, after the diſſolution of the former Parliament, and diverſe other things; But that accuſation was laid aſide, upou promiſe to perſwade the King to paſſe an act for a trienniall Parliament, and not to diſſolve this preſent Parliament without their own
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:161773:9"/>
conſent, and the like good ſervices to be done to the Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p>When the King went to <hi>Scotland, in Anno</hi> 1641. the Marqueſſe to ingratiate himſelfe with the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, joyned with the Earle of <hi>Argile</hi> and that faction, and upon pretence of a Plot againſt him by ſome Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers and ſouldiers, went from the Parliament of <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> to the Countrey with <hi>Argile,</hi> at which time the King declared publickly in Parliament, that however now he ſeemed to comply with them, he was the only man that incenſed him againſt that Kingdome; and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the other part, it is well knowne that <hi>Hamilt on</hi> even when he was his Majeſties Commiſſioner, often ſaid in private to the chief Covenanters, that nothing would prevaile with the King but force and neceſſity.</p>
            <p>In the yeare 1643. when the King had very neer ſubdued all his oppoſers in <hi>England,</hi> and reduced the whole Kingdome to his obedience, except <hi>London</hi> and three or foure Garriſons, and there was no probable meanes left for thoſe few members, who ſtiled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a Parliament, whereby to preſerve themſelves, or to oppoſe the King, but the calling in of the Sects, and when it was not poſſible, at the leaſt very difficult for the Covenanters to afford any conſiderable aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to their Confederates in <hi>England,</hi> if thoſe who profeſſed themſelves to be the Kings friends in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> had faithfully acted their parts, then <hi>Hamilton</hi> thought it time for him to paſſe over from the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanters and pretend for the King, that by having ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe to his Counſels, he might betray them, and diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point his deſignes. The Kings friends finding him thus enclined, procured great offers to be made to him from the King as to make him Duke, and give him in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:161773:10"/>
marriage the Prince Electors ſiſter, the Kings Neice, which he chearfully embraceth, and promiſeth to do great ſervices to the King.</p>
            <p>No ſooner doth he heare that the Queen is landed at <hi>Berlington,</hi> but with all expedition he repairs to her Majeſtie, to congratulate her ſafe returne. The Noble Marqueſſe of <hi>Montroſſe</hi> had before his comming ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted her Majeſtie what dangers were to be feared, from the Covenanters in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and that there was no way to prevent them, but that by authority from his Majeſtie, all the Kings friends ſhould riſe in Armes to oppoſe them. But <hi>Hamilton</hi> condemnes this as a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry raſh counſell, and undertakes by faire meanes to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the raiſing an Army in <hi>Scotland,</hi> if the King would truſt him with the managing of that buſineſſe; and to make it the more plauſible, he promiſed to do it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any trouble or expence to the King; whereupon a good King eaſily cozened with the faire pretences of one ſo neer in bloud, and ſo much obliged unto him, gives him abſolute truſt.</p>
            <p>When he returns to <hi>Scotland,</hi> he makes as great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions at home, as he had done abroad, &amp; would gladly have ſeemed to be the moſt zealous man living for the King in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ereſt; yet in al his actions croſſed the adviſe and Reſolution of the Kings friends. For the King being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſed, that the Covenanters had indicted a Conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Eſtates without his knowledg, wrote a letter to the Duke, and thoſe of the councell, to diſcharge the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention: but he concealing the letter, deſired the Earle of <hi>Callendor,</hi> to ſpeak with the <hi>Earle</hi> of <hi>Broxburgh,</hi> and ſome other Noble men beſt affected to his Majeſty, and to crave their advice; they all in one voice anſwered, that it was their Iudgement the King ſhould diſclaime
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:161773:10"/>
the Convention, and declare it illegall; but the Duke ſends them word by the Earle of <hi>Callendor,</hi> that it was the Kings minde to approve the Convention with ſome limitations; which though it made them to alter their adviſe, yet as it was related by the Duke, it was moſt falſe, the King never having had any ſuch things in his thoughts, untill it was ſuggeſted to him by <hi>Hamilton,</hi> as the advice of his friends in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and that there were hopes to carry matters in the Convention for the kings advantage, or at leaſt to hinder any aſſiſtance to be ſent to <hi>England</hi> againſt him: thus the king and his faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants in <hi>Scotland</hi> were deluded, and by <hi>Hamiltons</hi> policy, induced to countenance the Convention to the great prejudice of the kings affairs; but when they came there, yet the Duke and his brother <hi>Lanerks</hi> carriage in that convention, and after it, was no wayes according to what was promiſed in the conference with the Noble men that were affected to the king, of the truth whereof the Earle of <hi>Callendor</hi> and Mr. <hi>Murrey</hi> can particularly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme you, and how he would neither joyne with the kings friends, in a courſe of oppoſition, nor give his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, that they ſhould do it themſelves, without his perſonall appearance in the buſineſſe, but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary diſcouraged thoſe, who were willing and ready to take their lives in their hands, and to adventure all that was deareſt unto them for his Majeſty.</p>
            <p>When he had thus diſappointed the kings ſervice, then he and his brother <hi>Lanerk</hi> wrote letters to the king to advertiſe him, that very ſpeedily an Army was to come into <hi>England,</hi> and according to their promiſe, they had hindred them all ſummer, but could not hinder them any longer; ſhortly after theſe letters, the two bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren began their Journey to Court, where they found
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:161773:11"/>
their Juglings diſcovered to the King, and a proceſſe drawne againſt the Duke, wherein it was offered to be proved, that he was the occaſion of all the troubles and evils that have befallen theſe Kingdomes; in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, that he enticed the king to begin the War againſt <hi>Scotland,</hi> and in an underhand way, ſtirred up the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple againſt the king, by adviſing them not to yield, and bidding them inſiſt, and they would get their will, for he was a very coward, and that if he got his will, he would prove a greater Tyrant then <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ro;</hi> that he had mannaged all buſineſſes wherewith the king had truſted him, to his Majeſties diſſervice; particularly that he had given way to the preſent raiſing of an Army in <hi>Scotland</hi> againſt the king. There are divers other articles in that charge, ſome of them are coincident with what I have already written, though more largely expreſſed, and therefore I truſt you will excuſe me, that I have not ſent you a Copy thereof.</p>
            <p>The king upon conſideration of ſo hainous crimes, and treaſonable practices, committed the Duke Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to <hi>Pendennis,</hi> and ſhortly after his brother <hi>Lanerk</hi> eſcaped away from <hi>Oxford</hi> to <hi>London,</hi> where he was welcomed by the Scots Commiſſioners, and diſpatched away to their Army by ſea with letters of Recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and from the Army to <hi>Scotland,</hi> where he was inſtantly received to their Covenant, and admitted to their Counſels, and likewiſe to the Command of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>The Duke being priſoner, was not able, though wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling enough, to practice more againſt his Majeſty; yet <hi>Lanerk</hi> was not diſcouraged from proſecuting the old deſigne; for I do very well remember, that when the king was at <hi>New-caſtle,</hi> he was credibly informed, that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:161773:11"/>
upon a ſerious Conſultation amongſt the Covenanters, what inſtructions to ſend to the Scots Commiſſioners at <hi>London,</hi> concerning the king, who (as they ſaid) had been the Author of ſo much blood-ſhed in both king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, the Earle of <hi>Lanerick</hi> dropped theſe words, <hi>We can never have peace as long as this king, or any of his race re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains;</hi> and upon another occaſion, <hi>we can have no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence about Monarchicall Government; all the difference will be who ſhall be king.</hi> It may be he expects the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his horoſcope, whereof (as himſelfe ſince rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) he had ſo great confidence, when he was thought to be in danger, before his eſcaping from <hi>Oxford,</hi> ſaying that he was ſure he was not neere his death; for it was promiſed of him, that before he dyed, he ſhould be a greater man, then it was ſafe for him to mention. When the Duke was relieved from his impriſonment, and come to <hi>London,</hi> as I am informed, he had ſome expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, which diſcovered his reſenting his impriſonment; one expreſſion ſo far as I remember, was to this purpoſe, wherefore ſhould he go to the king, (then at <hi>New-caſtle:</hi>) for how could he ever truſt that man, who when he was in power impriſoned him?</p>
            <p>When he came to <hi>New-caſtle,</hi> he and <hi>Lanerick</hi> did un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to the king to bring him to <hi>Scotland,</hi> which if they had done, it had been an eaſie matter for the king to have engaged this kingdome and their Army, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring his Majeſty to his juſt rights in <hi>England;</hi> but it ſtood not with their deſignes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to have his Majeſty perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally preſent in <hi>Scotland;</hi> that would too much eclipſe their greatneſſe, and diſappoint their ends, and therefore they kept of the king with faire pretences from coming to <hi>Scotland,</hi> and all other reſolutions till a ſtrict Guard was put about him; And within a few dayes he was
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:161773:12"/>
delivered over to the Parliaments Commiſſioners. I cannot forget alſo to mention, how in the Parliament of <hi>Scotland,</hi> they made a faire ſhow in reaſoning for the king; but when it came to the Vote concerning his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery, the two brethren were in the negative them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but all their neereſt friends and dependers, whoſe voice they uſe to command as much as their owne, were in the affirmative.</p>
            <p>It may be remembred likewiſe how they kept cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with the Sectaries; for little good to his Majeſty (I ſuppoſe) if all the truth were known.</p>
            <p>However I perceive, that they have juggled ſo betwixt the king and his people, as they have got into their hands the Government of one Kingdome, though they dare not take off the maske; you will ſee that they will manage both peace and war, ſo as to keep power in their own hands; they will agree with any party to obtaine their ends, and let them pretend what they will for reſtoring the king, they will really obſtruct it: For let any rationall man judge, whether he that durſt take the boldneſſe in the dayes of his Majeſties proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to aſpire to the Crowne, will not in his Majeſties low condition, be ready to take the opportunity to proſecute the ſame deſigne. In the late declaration which you ſay is drawne by <hi>Lanerk,</hi> I ſee they pretend as faire for the Presbyterian Religion as for the king, when in reality, they are no further friends or enemies to any Religion, then may ſerve for their ends and ſtrengthen their intereſt againſt the king and his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, whereof there is no mention in that declaration; and let the Presbyterians think of them what they will, I make no queſtion, but if the Duke could be king of <hi>Scotland,</hi> his tender conſcience might without the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:161773:12"/>
help of Divines, be perſwaded to digeſt with a moderate Epiſcopacie, though we love not to buy it at that rate. How <hi>Abſalom</hi> like do they court the people with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences for the good of Religion, king and Kingdomes; as if they intended nothing, but to performe their vows in <hi>Hebron?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I conjure you by the dutie you owe to God, and the love you bear to the king and his poſterity, that you care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully take heed to their ſerpentine wayes, and give no beleefe even to their ſacreſt profeſſions or greateſt oaths; for then leaſt of all are they to be truſted, as I could eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cleare unto you from experience of their former dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings. But I will not further weary you, and thoſe doubting friends, to whom you are to communicate this letter, for whoſe cauſe I have been much larger, then I intended when I put pen to paper yeſternight. Touching the State of affairs here, and what courſe ſhall be taken in relation to <hi>Hamilton</hi> and his party, ſo as the kings affairs may ſuffer leaſt prejudice, I refer you to a letter from 123. and another from 271. And ſo reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Faithfull Servant,</signed>
               <dateline>London <date>May 23. 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
               <p>I forgot to mention that one of <hi>Hamiltons</hi> predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors in king <hi>Iames</hi> the ſixth his time, was forfeited by act of Parliament, for his aſpiring to the Crowne.</p>
            </postscript>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
